<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>coding on Dunder Doc</title>
    <link>http://stummjr.github.io/tags/coding/</link>
    <description>Recent content in coding on Dunder Doc</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2021 19:50:13 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    
      <atom:link href="http://stummjr.github.io/tags/coding/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How I manage Virtualenvs with Pyenv</title>
      <link>http://stummjr.github.io/post/how-i-manage-virtualenvs-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2021 19:50:13 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://stummjr.github.io/post/how-i-manage-virtualenvs-today/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have always been a happy &lt;a href=&#34;https://virtualenvwrapper.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&#34;&gt;virtualenvwrapper&lt;/a&gt; user, but I abandoned it last year to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pyenv/pyenv&#34;&gt;pyenv&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pyenv/pyenv-virtualenv&#34;&gt;pyenv-virtualenv&lt;/a&gt;. I don&amp;rsquo;t really remember why, as virtualenvwrapper is awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that lately I haven&amp;rsquo;t been creating and managing a lot of virtualenvs, so I often find myself having to search through pyenv docs to do basic stuff when needed. That&amp;rsquo;s why I
wrote down the usual steps that I follow so that next time I can remember (or find) more easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; this is not a comprehensive guide or tutorial on virtualenvs and pyenv. It&amp;rsquo;s just a collection of notes that I had on my note taking app that I thought that could be useful to someone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;installing-pyenv-and-pyenv-virtualenv&#34;&gt;Installing pyenv and pyenv-virtualenv&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how I install it on my Mac + Zsh:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ brew install pyenv pyenv-virtualenv
$ echo &#39;eval &amp;quot;$(pyenv init -)&amp;quot;&#39; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.zshrc
$ echo &#39;eval &amp;quot;$(pyenv virtualenv-init -)&amp;quot;&#39; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.zshrc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are other ways to install it, as you can see &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pyenv/pyenv#installation&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;updating-the-list-of-python-versions&#34;&gt;Updating the list of Python versions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every now and then a new Python version comes out and you&amp;rsquo;ll want to be able to install it.
To do that, you&amp;rsquo;ll have to update the list of Python versions that are available on your
local machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If pyenv was installed via homebrew as I did above, you can just run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ brew upgrade pyenv
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you manually installed pyenv by cloning the project repository, then you can run
this command to update your local copy of the repo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cd `pyenv root` &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git pull
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;installing-a-new-python-version&#34;&gt;Installing a new Python version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, list the versions available for installation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pyenv install  --list
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the version that you&amp;rsquo;re looking for is not listed, try the commands listed in the previous topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you found the target version on the list (let&amp;rsquo;s say it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;3.8.3&lt;/code&gt;), you can install it via:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pyenv install 3.8.3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-a-virtualenv-with-a-specific-version&#34;&gt;Creating a virtualenv with a specific version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say that you want to create a new virtualenv using the version you just installed (&lt;code&gt;3.8.3&lt;/code&gt;). You can do so via:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pyenv virtualenv 3.8.3 my-venv-3.8.3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;listing-virtualenvs&#34;&gt;Listing virtualenvs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pyenv virtualenvs
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;activating-a-virtualenv&#34;&gt;Activating a virtualenv&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pyenv activate my-venv-3.8.3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;deactivating-a-virtualenv&#34;&gt;Deactivating a virtualenv&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pyenv deactivate
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;activating-a-virtualenv-by-default-on-a-project&#34;&gt;Activating a virtualenv by default on a project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say that you have a project on a folder in your filesystem and you always want to activate
a given virtualenv when entering that folder. To do that, all you have to do is to place a
&lt;code&gt;.python-version&lt;/code&gt; file in that folder with the name of your virtualenv:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ echo &amp;quot;my-env-3.8.3&amp;quot; &amp;gt; .python-version
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it, now whenever you enter that folder, the virtualenv will be activated. This also
works for Python versions that you have installed via &lt;code&gt;pyenv&lt;/code&gt;, not just virualenvs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Abandoned Dark Mode</title>
      <link>http://stummjr.github.io/post/why-i-abandoned-dark-mode/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 15:55:13 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://stummjr.github.io/post/why-i-abandoned-dark-mode/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;15 years ago, my whole desktop environment was dark. Dark terminal, dark vim, dark graphic environment, and dark mp3 player.
It was pretty cool. I felt like a hacker in those unrealistic 90s movies. Whoever stepped into my room would think that I was
doing some rocket science. In fact, I was probaby just listening to mp3, learning some bash scripting and taking screenshots
to share my cool desktop in online forums. I can&amp;rsquo;t say it wasn&amp;rsquo;t fun, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 years later I started noticing how hard it had become to read/write code in my dark environment. My eyes would feel sore
and it was hard to focus on the code. Fonts were blurrier in my shiny retina display than they were in the 640x480 CRT monitors
I used back in the days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a bit of research, I found out that it probably happened because of my &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astigmatism&#34;&gt;astigmatism&lt;/a&gt;.
There are several scientific studies that show that people with astigmatism have trouble reading on &lt;em&gt;light-on-dark&lt;/em&gt; schemes.
I found out about them in this &lt;a href=&#34;https://ux.stackexchange.com/a/53268&#34;&gt;SE answer&lt;/a&gt;. People with astigmatism experience the so-called
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lexico.com/en/definition/halation&#34;&gt;halation effect&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spreading of light beyond its proper boundaries to form a fog around the edges of a bright image in a
photograph or on a television screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://jessicaotis.com/academia/never-use-white-text-on-a-black-background-astygmatism-and-conference-slides/&#34;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt;
to see how it feels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-i-fixed-the-issue&#34;&gt;How I fixed the issue&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To avoid this issue, all I did was changing my whole desktop to use a light background for everything. &lt;a href=&#34;https://ethanschoonover.com/solarized/&#34;&gt;Solarized Light&lt;/a&gt; is my favorite color scheme for my editor, terminal, and many other apps. This is how my development environment looks
like these days:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;http://stummjr.github.io/img/light-env.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not as cool as my screen two decades ago, but fully functional. 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;dark-backgrounds-are-everywhere&#34;&gt;Dark backgrounds are everywhere&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every week I see someone celebrating the fact that yet another app now supports dark backgrounds. The products announce it
as if they had found the cure for cancer. It&amp;rsquo;s kind of weird to see how far they go to announce a (&lt;em&gt;wait for it&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;) new color
scheme. Apple focused a MacOS release on something that most Linux graphical environments allowed me to do 20 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not preaching against dark backgrounds and in favor of light ones. In fact, most people that I know can&amp;rsquo;t code in a light
environment for too much time as they suffer from eye strain after a few hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a reader perspective, though, there are multiple studies showing that it&amp;rsquo;s harder to read in &lt;em&gt;light-on-dark&lt;/em&gt; than in &lt;em&gt;dark-on-light&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-gets-worse-at-conferences&#34;&gt;It gets worse at conferences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been in countless conferences where the speaker used a dark background to present snippets of code. Me during their talks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;http://stummjr.github.io/img/michael-scott-i-understand-nothing.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34;/&gt; 
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it wasn&amp;rsquo;t just me. You could see people squeezing their eyes all around the room. Sometimes even the speaker notices and
apologizes (or blames the video projector).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in a world where everyone can read well in dark backgrounds, there are still crappy devices and bad lighting
to ruin your talk. It&amp;rsquo;s not really common to find a conference with the right combination of light and good
projection devices. It&amp;rsquo;s probably hard and expensive to do so (I have no idea, to be honest).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But what can you, as a speaker, do?&lt;/strong&gt; Use light backgrounds for your slide decks and specially for the code snippets.
That will give you and your audience a better experience. As a bonus you also reduce the chances of having your talk
negatively impacted by an external factor like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;this-is-all-about-me-though&#34;&gt;This is all about me, though&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post talks about &lt;strong&gt;my personal experience&lt;/strong&gt; using dark vs light backgrounds. I am no doctor and I know nothing
about the human eye to give any sort of advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I feel it&amp;rsquo;s worth sharing what worked for me as there may be other people having similar issues and a light
background could be worth a quick try. In any case, a doctor is probably the right call. 😀&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; the snippets on this website will continue to use a dark background, just because it looks cooler. 😂&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
